A Guide to the Wine Family Papers, 1885-2001: SC 0273
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Wine Family Papers,
1885-2001
Special Collections, James Madison University
Wine Family
SC 0273
5.18 cubic feet; 13 boxes
The Wine Family Papers, 1885-2001, document three generations of the Wine family from Shenandoah County, Virginia. Their participation in civic engagement and community activities is documented through Sunday school minute books, ledgers, and diaries. The collection also comprises photographs, scrapbooks, postcards, and school materials documenting aspects of daily life.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Purchased at Laughlin Auctions, Inc.'s October 14, 2017 sale of the personal property from the home of Naomi Zirkle Wine of Woodstock, Virginia.
Appraisal Note
The nature of the auction was such that dissimilar or unrelated materials were bundled together in single lots. As such, these otherwise random materials were weeded and discarded. A large collection of newspaper clippings, comprised primarily of political cartoons, were also discarded. A representative sample of life insurance brochures and pamphlets were retained; duplicates were discarded.
Bio/Historical Information
Daniel P. "D.P." Wine (1855-1923) lived with his wife, Rebecca Good Wine (1855-1933), and their children on his family's ancestral Forestville, Virginia farm. D.P. Wine was a farmer and served as a minister and elder in the Flat Rock Church of the Brethren. Jacob David Wine and John Eugene Wine acted as executors to their father's estate after his death in 1923. Financial materials in the collection document their activities in settling the estate.
Jacob David "J.D." Wine (1881-1968), the eldest child of D.P. Wine and Rebecca Good Wine, attended Bridgewater College and married Kitty Sipe Huffman (1880-1947). He pursued his interests in Sunday school and church work, particularly with local Brethren churches and his home church – Flat Rock Church of the Brethren. J.D. was active in community and civic affairs including schools, roads, temperance, and local government. J.D. Wine, along with his father D.P. Wine, was a member of the Shenandoah County Anti-Saloon League. He also researched and published on local history and genealogy.
Jesse Clayton "J.C" Wine (1915-2016) was born to J.D. Wine and Kitty Sipe Huffman Wine of Forestville, Virginia. J.C. Wine married Naomi Catherine Zirkle (b. 1917) on September 4, 1943. During World War II, J.C. served as a civilian tailor at Fort Belvoir in the tailor shop and dry cleaners, later becoming its manager. He went on to sell insurance for the Union Life Insurance Company (ULICO) for more than three decades and retired in 1975. Outside of his professional pursuits, J.C. was an accomplished and talented cane maker and served his community as a charter member of the Woodstock Rescue Squad and as a member of the Woodstock United Methodist Church. During at least the early 1950s, J.C. Wine also served as the treasurer of the Mt. Jackson Methodist Charge which was comprised of the Mt. Jackson, Quicksburg, and Mt. Clifton churches. He was also a member of the Masonic Lodge and Shriners International.
Scope and Content
The Wine Family Papers, 1885-2001, document the personal and business activities of three generations of the Wine family of Shenandoah County, Virginia. Their participation in civic engagement and community activities is documented through Sunday school minute books, ledgers, and diaries. The collection also comprises photographs, scrapbooks, postcards, and school materials documenting aspects of daily life. Daniel P. "D.P." Wine, Jacob David "J.D." Wine, and Jesse Clayton "J.C." Wine are the predominant creators of the records present in this collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
Series 1: Personal Papers, 1885-1977
Subseries 1.1: D.P. Wine Papers, 1886-1938
Subseries 1.2: J.D. Wine Papers, 1894-1946
Subseries 1.3: J.C. Wine Papers, 1929-1977
Subseries 1.4: Non-Wine Papers, 1885-1909
Series 2: Photographs, 1897-1986
Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1903-1998
Series 4: Genealogical materials, 1892-2001
Series 1: Personal Papers is arranged into subseries by creator and further arranged chronologically. Series 2 through 4 are arranged chronologically. Exceptions to this arrangement scheme were made in order to group like materials together and as a result chronological arrangements are approximate.
Related Material
Wine Family. Papers, 1899-1943. Accession 42353, Personal Papers Collection, The Library of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia.
Separated Material
Numerous books and publications were pulled from the collection, cataloged individually, and added to Special Collections' rare book holdings. A series of Virginia maps were also separated and cataloged.
Bibliography
Wine, Jacob David. The Wine Family in America. First Section. Forestville, Va., 1952.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Shenandoah County (Va.) -- Church history; Shenandoah County (Va.) -- Economic conditions; Shenandoah County (Va.) -- History -- 19th century; Shenandoah County (Va.) -- History -- 20th century; Shenandoah County (Va.) -- History -- 21st century
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence); Genealogies (histories); Scrapbooks; Postcards; Photographs; Ledgers (account books); Diaries; Newsletters; Minute books; School records; Greeting Cards
- Series 1: Personal Papers, 1885-1977
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Personal Papers, 1885-1977, is arranged by creator into four subseries. The D.P. Wine sermon daybook is a bound ledger containing dates and types of sermons or ceremonies performed by Wine. Included are weekly church sermons with Bible verses referenced, funerals preached at by Wine, baptisms performed, and marriages in which Wine acted as the officiant. Loose handwritten obituaries were removed and foldered separately. Financial documents related to D.P. Wine's estate are included.
  The materials related to J.D. Wine primarily document his involvement in community organizations – the Lee District Sunday School Association, the Anti-Saloon League of Shenandoah County, and his local church council. His financial activities are documented in a series of ledgers and cashbooks.
  J.C. Wine's papers provide a more holistic view of his life and include materials relating to his early schooling, his career with the Union Life Insurance Company (ULICO), his involvement in church activities, and diaries written during the latter part of his life. The two diaries, 1970-1977, by J.C. Wine provide detailed daily accounts of local, national, and international happenings. J.C. documented notable news of the day (Richard Nixon's resignation, Apollo 14 mission), local births and deaths including the New Year babies born at local hospitals, weather reports, and personal and community updates. There are often numerous entries per day and the entries appear to reflect news likely reported in the local newspaper.
  Two miscellaneous items, an unidentified time book and a ledger presumably belonging to Samuel Good, are grouped together.
  - Subseries 1.1: D.P. Wine Papers, 1886-1938
    - D.P. Wine sermon daybook, 1886-1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Loose handwritten obituaries from D.P. Wine sermon daybook, 1886-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - D.P. Wine Farmers & Merchants Bank account book, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D.P. Wine canceled checks, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - D.P. Wine estate Farmers & Merchants Bank account statement and canceled checks, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - D.P. Wine estate Farmers & Merchants Bank account book, 1923-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - D.P. Wine estate citizens National Bank of New Market passbook, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - D.P. Wine estate Farmers & Merchants Bank account statement and canceled checks, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 1.2: J.D. Wine Papers, 1894-1946
    - J.D. Wine church council minute book, 1894-1904 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - J.D. Wine church council minute book, 1916-1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - J.D. Wine church council minute book, 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - J.D. Wine ledgers and cashbooks, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - J.D. Wine Anti-Saloon League of Shenandoah County minute book, 1909-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - J.D. Wine Lee District Sunday School Association minute book, 1919-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Loose programs and materials from Lee District Sunday School Association minute book, 1935-1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Loose Local Sunday School Reports from Lee District Sunday School Association minute book, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 1.3: J.C. Wine Papers, 1929-1977
    - J.C. Wine biology notebook (disbound), 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Book list of Shenandoah County Public Schools for the session of 1931-1932, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - J.C. Wine science workbook, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - J.C. Wine physical fitness certificates, 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - J.C. Wine Supervised Farm Practice Program certificates, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Cooperative Extension Work in Agriculture and Home Economics materials, 1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - J.C. Wine vocations workbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - J.C. Wine Old Testament workbooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - J.C. Wine New Testament workbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - J.C. Wine Treasure Island summary, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Roster and Telephone Directory of Officers and Non-Commissioned Officers Stationed at Fort Belvoir, Va., 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Assorted ULICO materials, 1937-1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - ULICO Sales Training Course workbooks, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - ULICO News, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - ULICO News, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - ULICO News, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - ULICO News, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - ULICO News, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - ULICO News, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - ULICO News, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ULICO News, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - ULICO News, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - ULICO Field Inspection Book (blank), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Life insurance lessons and worksheets, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - ULICO brochures, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Johnson's Motor Tuning Service Motor Testing Report, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - J.C. Wine car expenses notbeook, 1947-1953 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Constitution & By-Laws of the Shenandoah County Tuberculosis Association, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mt. Jackson Methodist Charge canceled checks and deposit slips, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Specifications for tailored suit by L.B. Branner for J.C. Wine, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Boys Service Club of Mt. Jackson programs and newspaper clippings, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - J.C. Wine car record book, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - J.C. Wine diary, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - J.C. Wine diary, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 1.4: Non-Wine Family Papers, 1885-1909
    - Samuel Good ledger, 1885-1909 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Timebook, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1897-1986
  Series 2: Photographs, 1897-1986, is comprised of loose photographs and bound photo albums primarily of Wine family members. The photographs, many of them identified, document Black Water Falls, Fort McHenry (Baltimore, Maryland), Fort Belvoir (Fairfax County, Virginia), Camp Bethel (Fincastle, Virginia), and scenes of daily life. Community members and friends are depicted (including John C. Myers, 1876-1962, of Broadway), as are family pets and animals. Photographs of Naomi Zirkle Wine's father's 90th birthday are included along with a register of the guests. Miscellaneous photographs include scenes of the National Mall in Washington, DC, the John F. Kennedy funeral procession, and persons who are likely community members or friends, but are otherwise unidentified. Additionally, a signed headshot of country music singer Roy Acuff and a signed facsimile of country music singers Lee and Juanita Moore and their son Roger Lee are included.
  - Unidentified photographs, 1897-1959, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Wine family photographs, 1933, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Wine family photo album, 1933, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Wine family photographs, 1933-1960, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wine family photo album, ca. 1938-1960, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Fort Belvoir photographs, ca. 1940s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Wine family photo album, ca. 1940s-1986 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Identified photographs, 1949-1976, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photo album, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - John F. Kennedy funeral procession photographs, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Joseph H. Zirkle's 90th birthday reception, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Country music photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Washington, DC National Mall photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photo album, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photo negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Wine family photo album, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1903-1998
  Series 3: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1903-1998, includes a large selection of blank postcards, both bound in scrapbooks and loose. The scrapbooks also contain greeting cards, with one documenting the birth of J.D. and Naomi Wine's daughter, Mary Sue Wine, and a second documenting J.C. Wine's various medical procedures and hospital stays during 1967-1972. One scrapbook is comprised of menus, newspaper clippings, programs for local music and theatre performances (New Market Theatre), beauty pageants, local church events, high school commencements (New Market, Triplett, Timberville), and related ephemera. Loose postcards depict local scenes as well as national landmarks and scenes of Washington, DC and New York City. Pamphlets and brochures related to J.C. Wine's involvement with the Masonic Lodge and Shriners International are included.
  - Kitty Huffman Wine postcard scrapbook, 1906-1927, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - J.D. Wine postcard scrapbook, 1907-1914, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Postcard scrapbook, 1932, undated (Box OV 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1932-1945, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Naomi Zirkle and J.C. Wine wedding scrapbook, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mary Sue Wine baby scrapbook, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Mary Sue Wine scrapbook, 1947-1952 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - J.C. Wine hospitalization scrapbook, 1967-1972 (Box OV 2)
  - Postcard scrapbook, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Non-Virginia postcards, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Real photo postcards, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Virginia postcards, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Religious pamphlets, 1903-1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Masonic ephemera, 1910-1951 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Masonic ephemera, 1952-1998, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Shriners ephemera, 1951-1952, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Assorted publications, 1931-1946 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Your Hit Parade song lists, 1939-1940 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Army pamphlets, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1945-1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Farming pamphlets, 1950, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - National Wildlife Conservation Stamps, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Political brochures, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Virginia brochures, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Series 4: Genealogical Materials, 1892-2001
  Series 4: Genealogical Materials, 1892-2001, document the Wine family and the related Myers, Zirkle, and Huffman families. The only correspondence in the collection is filed within this series as it relates strictly to Myers family history and their connection to the Wines. The letters are chiefly from Jennie R. Driver to J.D. Wine. J.D. Wine was a great-great grandson of Barbara Wine Myers and Samuel Myers.
  - Good family death memorial, Ida Florence Wine death memorial, 1892, 1899 (Box OV 1)
  - J.D. Wine correspondence, 1906-1926 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Catherine Garber Harpine correspondence, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Zirkle family genealogy, 1964-1966, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Huffman family genealogy, 1964-1971, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Wine family genealogy, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)